# Carolyn Jane Anderson

650 North Pleasant Street University of Massachusetts Amherst, MA 01003

Email: carolynander@umass.edu Web: http://candersl.github.io

#### **Research Focus**

My research focuses on context-sensitive expressions: words whose meanings change depending on who is speaking to whom, and where. These aspects of language are some of the most challenging for artificial intelligence to grasp, because they are situational, grounded, and interactive. Exploring these questions can help us understand general cognitive behavior such as theory of mind (our beliefs about other people's mental states), and help artificial intelligence learn to use language in a dynamic, responsive way.

#### **Education**

| <b>Ph.D. in Linguistics.</b> University of Massachusetts, Amherst<br>Dissertation: Shifting the Perspectival Landscape<br>Advisors: Brian Dillon and Rajesh Bhatt | February 2021 |
|---|---------------|
| M.A. in Linguistics. University of Massachusetts, Amherst   | May 2019      |
| <b>B.A. in Linguistics and minor in Computer Science.</b> Swarthmore College High Honors in Linguistics and Natural Language Models                               | June 2014     |

#### **Positions**

| Wellesley College, Computer Science Department Assistant professor  | Starting Fall 2021 |
|---|--------------------|
| BBN Technologies, Analytics and Machine Intelligence (Cambridge, MA)<br>Research Intern   | 2018–2019          |
| Fulbright Canada, University of Victoria and McGill University Fulbright Research Fellow, supervised by Leslie Saxon and Jessica Coon | 2014–2015          |

# **Funding**

| BBN Technologies Research Fellowship                 | 2019 and 2020 |
|--|---------------|
| Selkirk Linguistics Outreach Fund Award              | 2016          |
| University of Massachusetts Amherst Fellowship       | 2015-2016     |
| Fulbright Canada Research Scholarship                | 2014-2015     |
| Programming Languages Mentoring Workshop Scholarship | 2013 and 2014 |
| Marianne Durand Frey '57 Scholar                     | 2011-2014     |
| National Merit Scholar                               | 2010          |

### **Publications**

- 1. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. 2021. Tell Me Everything You Know: A Conversation Update System for the Rational Speech Acts Framework. *Proceedings of the Society for Computation in Linguistics* (SCiL) 2021.
- 2. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. 2021. Coming in, or going out? Measuring the effect of discourse factors on perspective prominence. *Proceedings of Experiments in Linguistic Meanings* (ELM) 1.
- 3. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. 2019. *Tomorrow* is not always a day away. *Proceedings of Sinn und Bedeutung* (SuB) 23. **Selected for oral presentation**.
- 4. Anderson, Carolyn Jane and Brian Dillon. 2019. Guess who's coming (and who's going): bringing perspective to the Rational Speech Acts framework. *Proceedings of the Society for Computation in Linguistics* (SCiL).
- 5. Anderson, Carolyn Jane and Brook Danielle Lillehaugen. 2016. Negation in Colonial Valley Zapotec. *Transactions of the Philological Society* 114(3).
- Anderson, Carolyn Jane, Nate Foster, Arjun Guha, Jean-Baptiste Jeannin, Dexter Kozen, Cole Schlesinger, and David Walker. 2014. NetKAT: Semantic foundations for networks. *Proceedings of the ACM SIGPLAN-SIGACT Symposium on Principles of Programming Languages* (POPL) 2014. Selected for oral presentation.

#### **Conference Presentations**

- 1. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. Diagnosing the semantics of perspectival expressions. Poster presented at the Annual Meeting of the Linguistic Society of America (LSA), 2021.
- 2. Anderson, Carolyn Jane and Tessa Patapoutian. Can neural network language models understand spatial perspective? Paper presented at the Bridging AI and Cognitive Science (BAICS) workshop, at the International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR), 2020.
- 3. Anderson, Carolyn Jane and Brian Dillon. Taking other perspectives into account: an RSA model of perspectival reasoning. Talk given at Rational Approaches in Language Science (RAiLS), 2019.
- 4. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. Explaining the progressive motion verb puzzle in Zapotec. Talk given at the Texas Linguistics Society, 2019.
- 5. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. *Tomorrow* isn't always a day away. Poster presented at the 31st annual CUNY Human Sentence Processing Conference, 2018.
- 6. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. The San Lucas Quiaviní Zapotec andative and venitive. Talk presented at the Society for the Study of Indigenous Languages of the Americas (SSILA) annual meeting, 2018. **Honorable Mention, Best Student Paper Presentation**
- 7. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. The andative and venitive construction in San Lucas Quiaviní Zapotec. Talk presented at Multi-Verb Constructions: Semantic, Syntactic and Typological Perspectives (MVC), 2017.
- 8. Anderson, Carolyn Jane and Brook Danielle Lillehaugen. The morphosyntax of negation in Colonial Valley Zapotec. Talk presented at the Society for the Study of Indigenous Languages of the Americas (SSILA) annual meeting, 2015.
- 9. Anderson, Carolyn Jane and Brook Danielle Lillehaugen. La morfosintaxis de la negation en el zapoteco del Valle colonial. Talk presented at Coloquio sobre Lenguas Otomangues y Vecinas (COLOV) IV: Mario Molina Cruz, 2014.

10. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. Language ideology and human rights doctrine in Morocco. Talk presented at New Ways of Analyzing Variation (NWAV) 42, 2013.

# **Manuscripts**

- 1. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. 2020. Shifting the Perspectival Landscape: Methods for Encoding, Identifying, and Selecting Perspectives. Dissertation, University of Massachusetts, Amherst.
- 2. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. 2019. Tomorrow isn't always a day away: Non-utterance time readings of *tomorrow*. Under revision.
- 3. Anderson, Carolyn Jane and Brian Dillon. 2019. Taking other perspectives into account: modeling the use of perspectival expressions in discourse. Ms., University of Massachusetts, Amherst.
- 4. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. 2017. The andative and venitive construction in San Lucas Quiaviní Zapotec. Ms., University of Massachusetts, Amherst.
- 5. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. 2014. I talk it and I feel it: Language attitudes of Moroccan university students. Honors thesis, Swarthmore College.

#### **Invited Talks**

"Guess Who's Coming to Dinner: a Bayesian approach to modeling perspective."

- Boston University, Department of Linguistics. 2020.
- Cornell Tech, Department of Computer Science. 2020.
- Colgate University, Department of Computer Science. 2019.
- Denison University, Department of Data Analytics. 2019.
- James Madison University, Department of Computer Science. 2019.
- Mount Holyoke College, Department of Computer Science. 2019.
- Occidental College, Department of Computer Science. 2019.
- University of Massachusetts, Amherst, Department of Computer Science. 2019.
- Wellesley College, Department of Computer Science. 2019.

#### Other Presentations

- 1. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. Reasoning about perspectives. Abstract selected for presentation at the Science Speed Geeking event at the XPrag Summer School, 2019.
- 2. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. Use your words (better): two projects on making better use of text for ASR. Intern presentation, BBN Technologies, 2019.
- 3. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. Neural networks for ASR: focusing on the text. Intern presentation, BBN Technologies, 2018.

# Teaching

| 1. Instructor, University of Massachusetts Amherst, Linguistics Department First Year Seminar: Technology for Language Revitalization                                     | Fall 2019   |
|---|-------------|
| <ol> <li>Teaching Assistant, University of Massachusetts Amherst, Linguistics Department<br/>Language Processing and the Brain (Instructor: Brian Dillon)</li> </ol>      | Fall 2019   |
| <ol> <li>Instructor, Mt. Holyoke College, Computer Science Department<br/>Programming Languages</li> </ol>  | Fall 2018   |
| <ol> <li>Teaching Assistant, University of Massachusetts Amherst, Linguistics Department<br/>Introduction to Linguistic Theory (Instructor: Seth Cable)</li> </ol>        | Spring 2017 |
| <ol> <li>Teaching Assistant, University of Massachusetts Amherst, Linguistics Department<br/>Cognitive Modeling (Instructor: Gaja Jarosz)</li> </ol>                      | Fall 2017   |
| Advising  |             |
| Research Assistants   |             |
| Carina Bolaños Lewen<br>Project: experimental work on perspectival motion verbs   | 2020-2021   |
| Tessa Patapoutian Project: experimental and computational modeling of perspectival motion verbs   | 2019-2020   |
| Alicia LeClair<br>Project: Perspectival motion verbs in Western Tlacolula Valley Zapotec  | 2017        |
| Awards  |             |
| Computing Research Association Outstanding Undergraduate Researchers Award Finalist   | 2014        |
| The Linguistics Prize in Applications of Theory, Swarthmore College   | 2014        |
| Phi Beta Kappa Inductee   | 2014        |
| Philip M. Hicks Prize for Best Critical Essay   | 2013        |
| Research Assistantships   |             |
| University of Massachusetts Amherst, Linguistics Department Research Assistant Primary investigator: Seth Cable Topic: Semantics of Endangered Languages in North America | 2017        |
| University of Massachusetts Amherst, Linguistics Department<br>Research Assistant<br>Primary investigator: Gaja Jarosz<br>Topic: Computational phonology                  | 2016        |

# Haverford College, Ticha Digital Humanities Project (Haverford, PA) Research Intern Advisor: Brook Lillehaugen Topic: Web-based preservation and presentation of Colonial Valley Zapotec texts Cornell University, Computer Science Department (Ithaca, NY) Research Intern, supervised by Nate Foster Topic: NetKAT: a domain-specific language for networking

# Service

| Ad hoc reviewer, Language                               | 2020      |
|---|-----------|
| Organizer, Neural Networks in Linguistics Reading Group | 2018-2020 |
| Volunteer, Skype A Scientist                            | 2020      |
| Graduate Representative to Faculty Meetings             | 2016-2017 |

# **Skills**

| Natural Languages   | Domain Specific Languages                                      |
|---|--|
| <ul><li>Bangla (novice)</li><li>French (advanced)</li></ul>                                   | PyTorch, TensorFlow, WebPPL                                    |
| <ul><li>German (intermediate)</li><li>Modern Standard Arabic (intermediate)</li></ul>         | Programming Languages  |
| <ul><li>Spanish (intermediate)</li><li>Western Tlacolula Valley Zapotec (fieldwork)</li></ul> | C++, Coq, Figaro, Haskell, Java, JavaScript, Python, R, Racket |